hey guys welcome to concept encoding
this is Shan and today in the part two
of transaction Management in the spring
board we are going to see a lot about
transaction manager and different ways
you can create a transaction like
declarative and programmatic right so
till now in the part one you have
already seen when we use add theate
transaction at the rate transaction
annotation what happened in the back
right how the framework actually invoke
an Interceptor and what that Interceptor
actually does okay so we actually pretty
much now familiar with at the rate
transactional its purpose now let's go a
little bit more deep okay so I want to
explain you first the hierarchy of
transaction manager okay so now here in
the hierarchy of transaction manager
this is the first the top layer
interface that is transaction manager
okay so this is generally an empty
interface there is nothing inside it so
this is the second which is very
important interface which we have is
platform transaction manager right this
is again an interface which has these
three
methods get transaction commit and roll
back right now if you just go little bit
up right and if you see that Interceptor
what Interceptor does is first create
transaction internally it might be doing
get transaction
only okay then it do complete inside
this complete uh this is under catch
right so this is a roll back flow so it
might be calling it's this roll back
method and after everything successful
when it try to commit it actually
internally invoking commit
method so this is actually the interface
which has these three methods now B
based upon what type of uh your like
whether you are using jpa whether you
are using jdbc or let's say if you are
using hibernate so there would be
different implementation of this but it
enforce all the transaction manager that
this three methods you have to implement
it okay so all these three methods are
present here but still it's an interface
somebody has to implement it and provide
the implementation so let's see that
what that the third part the third one
is abstract platform manager right so it
provide the default implementation of
this all these three methods right so
mostly uh there are different managers
right data source manager hibernate jpa
JTA right and jdbc so mostly their
Logics of this get transaction commit
roll back is same so this parent class
this abstract class parent class has
provided some default implementation and
this concrete
classes anything specific they have to
override it they are overriding it in
their respective classes right so this
is the third class abstract platform
transaction manager which is an abstract
class
okay which is a child of platform trans
manager and it provide an implementation
for all these three
methods now at the fourth layer what we
have is different type of transaction
managers as I already told you we can
have many right jdbc you know right with
jdbc you can talk with relational
database but with you have to write a
queries insert query you have to
manually write the query similarly jpa
Java persistent API so with this one
what you can have is you you can create
entity which can map with the table
right and most of the crud operation you
don't even have to write a query itself
you don't have to write insert you don't
have to write select so some are some
things got simplified with the
jpa then again hibernate is also a type
of jpa but it's totally different
framework so hibernate is also one of
the transaction manager okay and then
there is something called J at which is
Java transaction API which is
specifically used in the distributed
transaction so you remember we have
something called two-phase
commit right so this Java transaction
API JTA is getting involved when we have
to manage distributed transaction but if
in a local transaction if you're
managing you can pick anything right
jdbc hibernate jpa but again currently I
am all
it depend upon
which database you are using if you're
using relational database this works
fine you can talk with relational
database with anything jdbc data source
hibernate jpa right but let's say if you
are dealing with no SQL then you have to
change your library at the initial
itself I told you right uh once you
change the library you will get more
transaction managers which can take care
which can talk to no SQL
database okay but the underlying concept
would be same right these transaction
managers helps you to talk to a database
and helps to manage the
transaction
right okay now this things is clear that
what is the hierarchy of transaction
manager
okay so now we'll
see the type of transaction
management so there are two two type
declarative
and
programmatic declarative we have already
seen where we are using
annotation so when we are using at
theate transactional means it's a
declarative approach we are using so
transaction management through
annotation when we use declarative
approach spring boot hides lot of things
from us right so So based on the
underlying data source whether you are
using uh relational database or non-
relational database right is spring boot
will automatically choose a appropriate
transaction manager for us right in most
of the cases you will see that the
spring boot will choose jpa transaction
manager so many things got hidden from
us when we just use at theate
transaction okay so here if you can
see now here you can ask right hey sh if
I have to use if I have to use at theate
transactional but I have to tell spring
boot which transaction manager has to be
chosen right I don't want to work with
jpa I have to specifically use jdbc
transaction manager where I have to
write a specifically insert query right
a specific select query or let's say
that you are working with hiet you have
to tell springbot that hey choose hiet
don't by default pick JP so now you have
to tell spring boot which one to choose
how you will tell then Here app config
will come into the picture you already
know in the previous if you're following
the series that app config class you can
create with annotation at theate
configuration where we can create a bean
okay so there we can create a bean of
platform transaction manager which one
this one because this is a parent
interface now you can create an object
of
anyone right so now let's say that if
you have to tell a spring boot that hey
you have to work with data source
transaction manager you just create a
new data source transaction manager like
this this is we will see into the next
topic where we have to connect to a
database right data source so we have to
provide username password link URL so
that is just uh the way of connection to
a DB we have to get access right so but
the main part which I want to tell you
that if you don't want a spring to
automatically choose which transaction
manager you have to work with you can
specifically tell by creating a bean of
a platform transaction manager and
create an object of whatever you have to
work with whatever you are building a
project let's say hibernate you can
create a hibernate transaction manager
now when you will run right and uh at
you will put at the
transactional you can provide a
transaction manager like this now what
would happen is spring boot
will when it see at the transactional
and the value is like transaction
manager equals to this so what will do
spring boot will try to find a bean with
name user transaction manager so this is
the
name by by default when you create a
bean and if you don't provide a name
here by default this method name would
be considered as a name if you want some
specific name you can I think provide
name equals to something here and that
name you can give here but since I
haven't given any name here in the bean
so the method name would be considered
as a
name
okay so this is one declarative way of
using the
transaction there is another way called
programmatic okay programmatic means as
the name says you have to program right
you have to write the transaction
management logic in your code manually
so transaction management through code
it is flexible but difficult to maintain
definitely difficult to maintain because
if at 100 places you are you have to use
transaction so you have to write your
own code but why it's flexible where
exactly you might need it so let's
consider this use
case where this
programmatic might help you so now let's
say I have this method update user in
this this three operation happening
first is update DB so let's say some
initial set of DB operation and after
once this initial set of DB operations
are success
I need to make some external API
call and after this external API call I
have to update my DB again so you can
say that it's a final set of DB
operations so three operations first is
update DB then external API call then
again update DB something okay now if
you have put at theate transactional at
top of this
method it will cause an issue
why okay just pause it think for an
answer why it will cause an issue it
will cause an issue because external API
call is involved here now this external
API call let's say you are integration
with third party or some other U
component which is taking some time
which is uh taking let's say 3 4 seconds
to return you back right so now you are
holding your DB connections for that
time and at the time of peak traffic
where you have to open a large number of
DB connections to update it right this
external API call could be a bottleneck
because this is generally external API
calls are the time taking uh uh process
and because of this your DB connection
is in hold for that amount of time it
will not
complete okay so we and let's say that
you the best way you can do is try to
remove it but what I'm trying to say
that let's say that you have this kind
of dependency one 2 three you cannot
remove it you have to keep them
together in that case you can't use
transaction it will choke your system
during a p cards so in that case
programmatic can help
you okay so this is I'm telling you the
approach one of programmatic where you
are manually writing it everything so
this is I'm telling you the approach one
how you how we can write
it so in the approach one so let's say
this is the method name uh update user
programmatic I just let's say any method
you want to update DB right so
first from this manager hierarchy you
already know that you need a one
transaction manager object because this
only has get transaction commit roll
back so you need this this object and
for getting an object you have to
because it's an interface you can't
create an object of it you have to
create an object of only concrete class
so first step is very very clear that
this is the first step you have to get
an object
of platform transaction
manager which object right Which object
you want so in app config as we
discussed you can tell create a bean of
this platform transaction manager let's
say new data data source transaction
manager I want to use so during
application startup a bean would be
created for this one now you can use
this right either you can use Auto wir
here and you don't need Constructor
injection if you don't want to put at
theate autowire you can use Constructor
injection Constructor injection so this
user transaction manager
object will get a reference of this
Bean data source transaction manager so
first step is clear we got a platform
transaction manager object now
programmatically we have to create
transaction so first step is get
transaction we get the transaction now
what happen
is transaction is
created some transaction name would be
given right and other information would
be provided I will tell you what all
information we can give but it will
during this one if we haven't provided
anything by default it will uh spring
board will automatically choose a
particular name for a transaction and
other details but your transaction would
start so now once the transaction is
created now you can perform your task
right so now you can run queries up date
queries whatever you wanted and once
everything is successful we can use the
transaction manager and call commit it
will commit it if there is any issue we
will catch it and use the transaction
manager and call the roll
back okay so this is we are handling
manually right programmatic this is the
approach one where we are writing
everything so this is one way of
handling the programmatic there is
another better way so I would say that
this is the better
way of handling the programmatic so here
in this case right this all get
transaction commit roll back is still be
part of your code right so this is your
only business logic but this is still
part of your code so here spring boot
says that hey you can use transaction
template so transaction template which
we can use so here in the transaction
template considered it just as a
wrapper right so all this methods
right get transaction commit and roll
back it just wrapped inside it we'll see
how now this is this approach two so now
here what we are doing is we have to
first create an object of transaction
template okay now let's see
that here I again goes to the app config
at theate
configuration now here I am creating a
bean of transaction template transaction
template okay now when I'm creating a
transaction template bean I have to
provide
the one of the transaction manager like
what transaction manager you have to
use okay so let's say that I have
already created a bean platform
transaction manager right for I am using
new data source transaction manager
right so here I am providing this only
so when I'm creating a transaction
template there we can provide what
transaction manager you have to
use
okay using that itself you would be able
to so now you can put at the rate
autowired here here itself you don't
need Constructor injection for this or
if you don't want to put at theate Auto
Constructor injection you can use it now
what would happen is uh spring would
look for this transaction template Bean
if it found it it will assign a
reference to this so now this is the
first you have to create an object of
transaction template here now here if
you see in the transaction template
there is a method called
execute now in the execute
what is
the parameter it accept is transaction
call back which is a functional
interface I have already explained what
how to how do you handle functional
interface and Lambda expression in my
Java uh playlist so here I considered
that you already know what is function
interface and how to write a Lambda
expression so transaction call back
here we have a meth me called do in
transaction so what exactly we have to
pass here is the method your business
logic which you want to run what
template is that so it has provided a
template so template generally we can
say that the blueprint so what it does
is it will get
transaction then it will have your call
back call back function whatever so this
is actually your business logic
this is your
business logic like your insert queries
update queries whatever the you want to
update and then there is a commit and
roll back if
required right so it will catch it and
roll back it something but you got it
right so this template uh this
transaction template has provided us a
blueprint hey get transaction now we can
tell get a transaction of this
transaction man man after that we will
pass the call back function that where
we have actually our business logic so
this will run it after that it will do
commit and roll
back okay so now the same thing which
I'm going to do first I have created an
object of this transaction template now
I am calling the execute method now in
the execute method this is
the call back function you have to class
so here I am creating a my call back
function and I've already shown you this
is a functional interface so I am using
a Lambda expression to pass
my business logic here as a function
okay so here if you
see I am passing
my business logic insert query update
query whatever I wanted to update into
this method I passed here right and then
I passed
this into this execute method it will
first get transaction right when it do
get
transaction this is the transaction
manager it is using which we are telling
right this transaction manager it is
using so it will invoke proper gr
transaction
method after that here it is doing do in
transaction means ultimately it is
calling our business
logic right so the same thing we it has
done get transaction then our business
logic is
running after that if any issue happen
it is doing roll back or if any uh
everything is Success it does
commit so it just little cleaner
approach of doing this but this is also
one way of doing a
programmatic transaction handling by
using using transaction
template
so I hope this two parts declarative and
programmatic is clear
now there is one very very important
part is we have to understand is
propagation so what uh propagation means
is when we try to create a new
transaction right when we try to create
a new transaction it first check the
prop propagation value set now based on
that propagation only it will create a
transaction okay it will get clear to
you once we go through all right so now
let's see this and when you will uh read
this line again it would be very much
clear to you now suppose that you
already have a
transaction you have already have a
transaction method one
you are doing something something
something now you are internally
invoking method
two now this method
two is also is at the rate
transaction so internally for this
method one when you have put at theate
transaction there internally it might
have done get transaction right
the Interceptor would have intercepted
it and Interceptor have done
this create transaction if necessary see
this condition if
necessary okay so internally it might
have done get transaction
only and here when the method two is
invoke there also we have put at the
rate transaction means internally it
also tried to get a trans
transaction okay so this is inside this
and this get transaction so it is inside
this and it is try to a get transaction
so this is for method
two this is for method
one okay now see the question comes in
the interview also and it should comes
to you also hey when method one is
invoked we try to take one transaction
and transaction let's say created
transaction
one now all the operations are happening
within a particular transaction now
method two invoke now method two also
does get
transaction right and this method two
also has certain logic so now this
method to logic would be a part of this
transaction one or new transaction would
be created and it would be part of that
one so what what would
happen that's where the propagation
comes into the
picture so let's go through one by one
and it will help you to understand
better the first propagation is required
and this is also a default so whenever
we have put at theate transaction we
haven't Pro provided what is the
propagation so by default what is the
propagation it has
chosen required propagation do required
if you have to provide it specifically
you can do like at theate
transactional propagation equals to this
required and if you even if you don't
write it by default the propagation is
required only so what this required says
that if parent transaction
present right so let's say that uh
transaction one is already present this
is for method
one now now for method two it is it want
it it want to create a new transaction
so method 2 want to create a new
transaction we have put at theate
transaction here right so whether method
2 can can create a new transaction or
not if parent transaction present use
the same one right so it will not create
any new transaction no it will use the
same
transaction else create new one if there
is no parent transaction present then
only it will create a new
one okay so let's see that with an
example it will clarify you so now when
I start the server and let's say that I
am hitting an
API so what happened so here if you
see it will invoke this method one this
method one is under transaction so let's
see this two values what it
is is transaction active true yes this
is active because already it is inside a
transaction and what is the current
transaction name it has uh spring boot
has given to us it is this com concept
and coding learning spring boot this
method one so it has given the complete
class path uh the method class path as a
name itself Okay so one transaction is
created now it has doing some operations
and internally it called method two
which is again g a
transaction okay which is of required
type okay just uh in the
system.out.print end it is uh I have
printing required new but consider it as
a required because we have changed it
for understanding so now method two got
invoked now during method two got
invoked at theate transaction it will
try to do get transaction internally
Interceptor but the propagation it will
check in the propagation it will check
whether it has to create a new
transaction or not required required
says that if parent transaction exist
use that one don't create a new
transaction so is actual transaction
active yes this method is also running
inside a transaction that's why it said
true what is the name of the transaction
inside which this method is running if
you you see the same method one the same
as the parent
one right it didn't create a new one so
required is clear required new required
new says
that if parent transaction
present suspend the parent transaction
for a while suspend doesn't means that
it has been aborted no aborted and
suspend both are different things so it
there it will suspend the parent
transaction for a wife
then what it will do is it will create a
new transaction for this method two and
it will perform its operation in a new
transaction and once that new
transaction is committed or roll back
whatever after that it will resume the
parent
transaction so this is like if parent
transaction present if parent
transaction doesn't present it will
create a new transaction and execute the
method so let's see that
now here from the method one I am
calling method two now change it to
required
new okay now let's start the server
again the API
again okay now let's see what
happening so first method one is
it is it inside the transaction yes what
is the method name
put a current transaction name some
current transaction name it would put
right method one
complete now it is doing some initial DB
operation it has printed now it is
calling method two now method two is
also under transactional but required
new so what it will do is it will
suspend the parent transaction for a
while now parent transaction is is in
weight State now this method to create a
new transaction so this method two is
running inside a transaction
yes what is the transaction name inside
which it is
running now here if you see this name is
different than this
one okay and once it is finished it
committed then it will resume the parent
one so now the parent
one some final DB operation it will get
printed okay so you got it required new
means you always need a new transaction
if parent already has you will stop it
then create a new one once finished then
resume the
parent then we have
supports support means that if parent
transaction present use it else execute
the method without any transaction you
don't need any transaction for the
method two right so here in the method
two when you do like here
support supports so if parent
transaction added it will use it if
parent transaction doesn't exist it it
will not create any transaction at all
for this method to it will not create
any
transaction not
supported if parent transaction present
suspend the present
transaction execute the method without
any
transaction and once without any
transaction this method is completed
then resume the parent
transaction if parent transaction
doesn't exit itself execute without any
transaction so this not supported means
that no matter if parent transaction
exit or not it will execute the method
without any transaction
only then we have something called
mandatory mandatory says that if uh if
parent transaction present use it
otherwise throw exception so this
mandatory is like parent transaction
should be
present so there here you can use like
mandatory which says that parent
transaction should be present so from
where this method get invoked it should
also be inside a transaction it never
creates a new
transaction otherwise it will throw
exception then there is something called
Never right uh so it's uh you can change
it
to never so what says that if parent
transaction par uh present it will throw
exception right else execute the method
without any transaction never says that
parent also should not have any
transaction from where it is getting
invol right if it is present it will
throw exception otherwise it will
execute the method without any
transaction so these are the different
ways of
propagation and you already know that
when you are using a declarative way you
are using at theate transaction how you
can provide the propagation right you
can provide the propagation like this
now we can check all this uh logic if
else which I'm telling you it should be
present into this what was the
transaction Interceptor so this was the
class right transaction Interceptor
inside that method
create
transaction if necessary yeah so this
create transaction if necessary calls
this method get transaction so what it
is doing is existing
transaction if it is an existing
transaction how to handle it so it will
check propagation never if propagation
never throw an exception right uh
propagation not supported like
propagation required new if propagation
is required new then it will suspend the
parent one and then it start a new
transaction so everything is is already
doing it right the spring framework does
the same thing right it just like we can
double check our understanding through
the
code now you can ask me right okay uh we
got it like how we can pass the
propagation uh through declarative but
what about programmatic way of how in
the programmatic way we
can assign this propagation approach one
where we are writing everything so what
is the first step the first step
is getting an object of platform
transaction manager and how you will get
an object you can there would be one app
config in the inside an app config you
can create a bean of platform
transaction manager and whatever the
transaction manager you can create a new
of
that okay so now here what happen is now
you have the object now you have to call
get transaction now when you're doing
get transaction right if you remember
earlier we passed null here now we are
passing transaction
definition so I have created a def uh
object of transaction
definition right and I have said two
things one is name I told you right
earlier if you don't provide any name
springboard will give the random name or
uh any name to a transaction but if you
want a specific name to be choosen for a
transaction you can put into a
definition and the propagation which you
want I want propagation required so you
can put it and pass into the
definition
okay so very
simple now in the approach to where we
are using transaction template how we
can pass the propagation is so the first
step is very very clear that we have to
create an object of a transaction
template and how we can create an object
of transaction template in the app
config configuration we have to create a
transaction template object which has
the transaction manager as a parameter
what transaction manager we
wanted but after after that itself
instead of returning from here we can
also set hey this template this is the
propagation Behavior I wanted whether
required not required never mandatory
Etc and any name you have to want to
give a transaction you can also set a
name and then
return now exactly the same thing which
we have done
before okay so I hope this declarative
and programmatic is clear in the next
part I will tell you about the isolation
level and okay guys thank you bye